younglife.org 2019-11-05

# Young Life Global Privacy Statement

​ **б​ългарски** | **Č​esk​y** ​  
| **Deutsch​​​** | **Francais​** | **Polskie**​ | 

View our  
 **Childr​en's Privacy Policy**  
  
---|---|---|---|---|---  
  
### Your Privacy

**LAST UPDATED MAY 2018  **

Young Life exists to introduce adolescents to Jesus Christ and help them grow in their faith. ​Young Life is actively pursuing this mission with middle school, high school and college-aged kids in all 50 of the United States as well as more than 90 countries around the world.  

To further this global mission, Young Life and its various related ministry organizations (Young Life) may collect, process, use, and share your personal information. The purpose of this Privacy Statement is to explain to you how Young Life might use your personal information and how Young Life takes seriously its obligation to you to protect your rights and your personal information.

Where we use the terms “Young Life,” “we,” “us,” and “our,” we refer to Young Life, a Texas nonprofit corporation, and its subsidiaries and affiliated organizations. “Personal information” generally refers to all data that directly or indirectly relates to you, but “personal information,” “personal data,” or “personally identifiable information” and other terms may apply based upon applicable law and will carry the meaning of those applicable laws.

From time to time, we may update this Privacy Statement, so we encourage you to review this statement periodically, paying special attention to the “LAST UPDATED” date above. In certain circumstances, Young Life may contact you to specifically notify you of changes to this Privacy Statement.

**Young Life’s Commitment to Data Protection**  

It is the global policy of Young Life to exercise a high standard of care in its handling of the personal information it collects, processes, uses, and shares. Young Life will maintain appropriate policies and processes throughout the global mission to enhance the protection of personal data and ensure compliance with applicable laws and regulations. Young Life is also committed to the periodic review and augmentation of these policies and processes as part of its Global Privacy Program.  

**Laws That Apply to This Privacy Statement**  

Young Life is a global organization which maintains data protection policies and practices consistent with accepted international data privacy principles. These policies supplement national data privacy laws, and any national law takes precedent in the event it conflicts with Young Life’s policies. In Europe, the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) is in effect as of May 25, 2018. If GDPR and/or other EU privacy laws apply to you, this Privacy Statement describes how you can exercise your rights.  

**What Kinds of Information We Collect**  

Young Life collects the following types of personal information:

**_Contact information:_** Includes phone number, physical address, SMS, email address, telephone number, social media profile details. 

**_Demographics:_** Includes information about who you are, where you live, and what programs and activities in Young Life may be of interest to you.

**_Employment information:_** Includes information required to process your employment application and complete your employee onboarding process, such as employment history, references, criminal conviction records, unique qualifications or vocational preferences.

**_Financial History:_** Includes historical information on your donations to Young Life, services or goods purchased from Young Life, other financial transactions you have entered into with Young Life.

**_Identity Data:_** Includes name, date of birth, gender, marital status.

**_Information about Personal Beliefs:_** Includes religious information.

**_Payment Information:_** Includes bank account and routing numbers, credit card/debit card numbers, check number, other pertinent financial details.

**_Requests and Preferences:_** Includes your preferences for how Young Life will communicate with you, customizations you have made to any Young Life account.

**_Required Health Data:_** Includes health information required by Young Life for you to attend a Young Life camp or participate in a Young Life trip or event, including medical history, vaccination records, physician’s reports, and biometrics.

**_Security Credentials:_** Includes login and password information.

**_Travel information:_** Includes requests related to your travel with Young Life, passport information, dietary needs or restrictions.

**_Volunteer Information:_** Includes information required to process your volunteer application and complete your volunteer onboarding process, including references, criminal convictions records, unique qualifications.

**_Young Life information:_** Includes information on your history and engagement with Young Life.

**How We Use Your Personal Information**  

Young Life uses the personal information you provide to better serve your requests and to connect you further with the mission and ministry activities of Young Life. Whether you are involved in a Young Life club or camp program or donating your time and/or money to our missional objectives, Young Life will generally use your personal information to achieve its legitimate interests related to our organizational mission. We do not sell, lease or rent your personal information to others. Young Life will only process your personal information in accordance with an appropriate legal basis and only for the purposes described in this Privacy Statement. The table below provides a list of examples of how we may use your information, the types of information involved, and the legal basis for our use of your information.  

​How We Use Your Personal Information | ​The Types of Personal Information Involved | ​Legal Basis | ​Examples and Explanations  
---|---|---|---  
​To contact you with information about the ministry activities that Young Life offers in your local area. | ​Identity data, Contact information  | ​Legitimate Interests | ​A Young Life staff member or volunteer may use your name and phone number or email to invite you to a Young Life club activity in your local area.  
​​To facilitate your attendance at a Young Life camp and to follow up with you after your attendance. | ​Identity data, Contact information, Required Health Data, Requests and Preferences, Demographics, Payment Information, Travel Information | ​Contract | ​We think you will have the best week of your life if you attend a Young Life camp. We will need certain information from kids and parents in order to facilitate the camp experience.  
​To facilitate your participation in a Young Life trip. | ​Identity data, Contact Information, Required Health Data, Requests and Preferences, Demographics, Payment Information, Travel Information | ​Contract | ​Young Life has some amazing short term mission trips, but we need personal information to assist with coordinating travel and communicating important information about the trip.  
​To assist you in establishing an account on Young Life’s network. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Requests and Preferences, Demographics, Security Credentials | ​Contract and Legitimate Interests | ​Whether you are attending one of our events or are a faithful donor to Young Life, we want you to be able to easily interact with us. Therefore, we use different network solutions to enhance your experience with Young Life.  
​For electronic marketing communication related to Young Life’s ministry activities or related to opportunities to donate to Young Life. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information | ​Consent or Legitimate Interests | ​We love to let you know about Young Life opportunities of which you may not already know, but we don’t want to send you communications you don’t want. If you have engaged with us before, we believe we can legally contact you with electronic marketing communications. However, we want you to be in control, so please let us know if you don’t want to receive this kind of information.    
​For physical communication (e.g. post, telephone calls, etc.) related to Young Life activities. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information | ​Legitimate Interests | ​We still use the postal service from time to time to communicate with you about your engagement with Young Life and to let you know important updates about our work with kids.  
​For non-marketing electronic communications to keep you informed on Young Life news and updates. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information | ​Legitimate Interests | ​Our staff members often update interested donors and friends with stories and information on what they are doing in their ministries.  
​To allow you to apply to serve Young Life as a staff member or a volunteer. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Information about your Personal Beliefs, Requests and Preferences, Security Credentials, Demographics, Young Life Information | ​Contract | ​Young Life carefully vets potential staff and volunteers to ensure their fitness to join in our work with kids.  
​To facilitate your registration for a Young Life fundraising activity and follow up with you after the event. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Payment Information | ​Contract | ​A Young Life staff member or volunteer may invite you to join in a local golf tournament or banquet to learn more and support the work of Young Life in your local area.  
​For contact management. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Requests and Preferences, Demographics | ​Legitimate Interests | ​We work hard to manage your information within our system in the most efficient way possible so we can quickly respond to your requests related to Young Life or related to your rights or personal information.  
​To provide ministry services such as spiritual guidance or Biblical counsel. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Information about your Personal Beliefs | ​Legitimate Interests | ​We believe God loves you and God loves kids, and our staff and volunteers want to be present in the lives of kids to hear what they are going through and demonstrate the love of Christ.   
​To employ you as a Staff Member of Young Life. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Information about your Personal Beliefs, Requests and Preferences, Security Credentials, Demographics, Employment Information | ​Contract and Legal Obligations | ​In order to work for Young Life, you must provide certain personal information to facilitate your employment.  
​To facilitate your volunteer activity for Young Life. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Information about your Personal Beliefs, Requests and Preferences, Security Credentials, Demographics, Volunteer Information | ​Contract and Legal Obligations | ​In order to volunteer for Young Life, you must provide certain personal information to facilitate your volunteering.  
​To process your donations. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Payment Information | ​Contract and Legal Obligations | ​When you give to Young Life, we will ask you to provide information necessary to complete your donation and create appropriate records.  
​For legal reporting obligations. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Payment Information, Financial History, Employment Information, Volunteer Information | ​Legal Obligations | ​Young Life is subject to certain government reporting obligations and this reporting may include your personal information but only to the extent that Young Life is legally obligated to supply this information.  
​To deliver Young Life goods and services. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Payment Information, Young Life Information | ​Contract | ​You may want to purchase a t-shirt or mug from our online store, or you may want to sign up for a golf tournament.  
​To solicit feedback from you on Young Life ministry activities, good and services. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Requests and Preferences, Security Credentials, Demographics, Young Life Information | ​Legitimate Interests | ​You may be asked from time to time to provide feedback on an event so that we are constantly getting better.  
​To respond to your requests. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Requests and Preferences, Security Credentials, Demographics | Legal Obligations​ | ​We use your personal information to quickly respond to any request you have for Young Life.  
​To respond to your complaints. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Requests and Preferences, Demographics | ​Legal Obligations | ​We use your personal information to quickly respond to any complaint you have against Young Life and to quickly respond to any concern about your rights and personal information.  
​To satisfy child safety laws and regulations. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Employment Information, Volunteer Information | ​Legal Obligations | ​Young Life performs periodic criminal background checks and driver’s questionnaires as part of our commitment to the highest standards of child safety.  
​To keep interested friends of Young Life involved in ongoing Young Life ministry. | ​Identity Data, Contact Information, Requests and Preferences, Demographics, Young Life Information | ​Legitimate Interests | ​Young Life has an entire ministry initiative dedicated to staying in touch with alumni of Young Life called Young Life Alumni and Friends. The Alumni and Friends website and program allows you to connect with other people who have been involved in and care about Young Life. The Alumni and Friends site also provides a prominent option for opting out of further contact or communication.  

**How Information is Collected**  

We obtain personal information about you in the following ways:

  1. Personal interactions:  The ministry of Young Life is defined by relationships. Our staff members and volunteers interact regularly with kids, parents, teachers, school administrators, coaches, donors, and many other individuals. These personal interactions are a primary avenue by which Young Life gets information from you.
  2. Direct Requests:  You may have reached out to Young Life on your own or visited one of our websites. If you have inquired about a Young Life activity, engaged in a Young Life activity, made a donation, registered for an event or camp, or have otherwise chosen to give Young Life Information, we have your personal information. Please read this Privacy Statement carefully to understand your rights and our commitments related to your personal information.
  3. Cookies and Other Automated Technologies:  If you have visited and/or registered on a Young Life website, some of your personal information may have been gathered by cookies or other automated technologies utilized on the Young Life network.  Read the section below on Young Life’s use of cookies for additional information.

**How and When We Might Share Your Information**  

Young Life does not generally disclose personal information with anyone outside the organization. However, Young Life is a global organization who may, for the purposes described above, share your personal information with:

  1. Other parties within or associated with Young Life.
  2. Public or regulatory organizations for obligatory purposes described above.
  3. Third party service providers Young Life has contracted to assist in the types of uses described above, including web-based contact management service providers, cloud service providers, companies assisting in the processing of your donations or other financial transactions, and email marketing service providers. Young Life has entered into contracts with these third party service providers without neglecting the protection of your personal information.  

**International Data Transfers**  

Young Life is a global organization operating in different parts of the world through branch organizations, subsidiaries, and affiliates.  Therefore, Young Life may transfer your personal information from one country to another. All individuals in the European Economic Area or the United Kingdom need to be aware that we may transfer your personal information outside of the European Economic Area or the UK for processing.  

Any transfer of personal information from country to country will be done with appropriate safeguards and in compliance with applicable laws. Young Life and its European subsidiaries and affiliates have established standard contract clauses to govern the transfer of data from the European country to other countries, such as the United States.

**Your Rights**

If you are located in the European Economic Area or the United Kingdom, you have certain rights related to your personal information. If you wish to exercise any of those rights, please email Young Life at privacy@younglife.org. We will respond to your request within 30 days. We may need to verify your identity in order to process your request.

These European rights include:

  1. Right of access

You have the right to know that we are processing your personal information, how we are processing this information, and for what purposes. This Privacy Statement is intended to provide the transparency necessary for you to know this information, but you can certainly make additional inquiries to Young Life by emailing privacy@younglife.org. 

  2. Right to Edit and Update Information

You have the right to rectify inaccurate information, update your personal information, and supplement incomplete information in the Young Life networks. Young Life’s network solutions will often allow you to make these changes on your own by managing your online Young Life account. Where this feature is not accessible, you can contact Young Life by emailing privacy@younglife.org, and we will address your request without undue delay.

  3. Right to Delete Personal Information

You have the right to request us to delete your personal information for the following reasons:  
a) If the data is no longer necessary for the purposes it was collected.  
b) If you withdraw previously given consent where consent is required to process the information.  
c) If you object to Young Life processing the data in a certain way or for certain purposes and Young Life does not have legitimate grounds to continue processing the information.  
d) If your personal information has been unlawfully processed.  
e) If your personal information must be erased to comply with a legal obligation.  
f) If the personal information has been collected in relation to the offer of Information Society Services as defined in Article 8(1) of the General Data Protection Regulation.

We may be required to reject your request to delete your information for the following reasons:  
a) For exercising the right of freedom of expression and information.  
b) For compliance with a legal obligation.  
c) For reasons of public interest as described in Article 17 of GDPR.  
d) For the establishment, exercise or defense of legal claims.

To make a request to delete information, you can email Young Life at privacy@younglife.org. We will notify you within 30 days as to whether your request has been accepted or if and for what reason we cannot fulfill your request. 

  4. Right to Request the Limitation of Processing Personal Information

You have the right to restrict our processing of your personal information for the following reasons:  
a) If you believe your personal information is inaccurate, you can request that we limit our processing of the data until its accuracy is verified.  
b) If the processing of your data is unlawful, you may either request erasure as described above or request certain restrictions.  
c) If the controller does not need the information for the purposes above but must retain the information for the establishment, exercise or defense of legal claims.  
d) If you have objected to the processing of your personal information and there is a pending determination as to whether our legitimate grounds to process override your rights described here.

As with any request for erasure of your personal information, you also have the right to be notified by us about a restriction in the processing of your personal information.

You can make this request by emailing Young Life at privacy@younglife.org.

  5. Right to Portability

You have the right to request us to send you your personal information in a structured, commonly used, machine-readable format so that it can easily be transferred and used by a third party if:

a) You provided us with the information.  
b) The processing of your personal information is based on your consent or required for the performance of a contract; or  
c) The processing is carried out by automated means.

You can make this request by emailing Young Life at privacy@younglife.org.

  6. Right to Object and Automated Individual Decision-making

You have the right to object to our processing of your data when our legal basis for processing is Young Life’s legitimate interests based on your particular situation. Upon receiving an objection from you, Young Life will cease to process your information unless we can demonstrate compelling legitimate grounds for the processing which overrides your rights and freedoms.

Particularly, you have the right to object to the processing of your personal information related to direct electronic marketing.

You also have the right to object to our processing of your information where decisions on processing are made by automated processing which has a legal or other significant impact on you.

You can make this request by emailing Young Life at privacy@younglife.org.

  7. Right to Withdraw Consent

Young Life is primarily processing your information based on our legitimate interests and other obligations. However, where you have given consent to us to process your personal information, you have the right to withdraw that consent and we will promptly respond.

You can make this request by emailing Young Life at privacy@younglife.org.

  8. Right to File a Complaint with the Data Protection Authority

We want to provide the best service to you related to these requests and resolve any issue you have with Young Life related to the processing of your personal information. You, however, always have the right to contact your local data protection authority for assistance or to make a complaint.

While the rights explained above do not apply to those outside of the European Economic Area and the UK, as a matter of rights and freedoms, we still do care about your questions and concerns related to your personal information. If you are not located in the European Economic Area or the United Kingdom, you can contact Young Life at privacy@younglife.org with questons.

**Security**

To safeguard and secure the information we collect, Young Life has applied appropriate physical, electronic and managerial procedures to prevent unauthorized access and maintain data accuracy. The Secure Socket Layer (SSL) protocol is used where available to encrypt and protect all Internet data transmissions. The padlock icon in your browser’s window signifies that a site is secure. Sometimes password protection is used to protect your privacy and security. Young Life will continue to augment current security procedures and adopt new security protocols as necessary to meet the standard of care we have promised in our policies and in this Privacy Statement.

Young Life is also committed to a prompt response to any potential data breach and has instituted a Data Breach Protocol Process which includes timely notices as required by applicable law. 

**Information Collected by Cookies or Technology**

Young Life websites may use cookies to recognize you and may allow you to automatically log in without re-entering your user name and password every time you visit our site. The cookies are encrypted and may store limited personally identifiable information about you, including your name, user name and email address. If cookies are disabled on your browser, you may be able to still use a Young Life website, but you will be required to enter your password each time you visit.

**Information Related to ​Children**

In general, Young Life websites are informational sites for parents and children about Young Life. It is our intention to provide a safe, fun environment where children and their parents may explore Young Life, their own Young Life club and other Young Life activities. None of Young Life’s websites knowingly solicit personal information from children under the age of 13, except where personal information must be solicited from children and/or parents to facilitate participation in Young Life events or activities.

We care about children’s privacy and we take great care to safeguard the personal information of all children. We do not require a child to supply us with any personal information other than is necessary to participate in a specific activity, and we never condition a child's participation in an activity on the child's disclosing more personal information than is reasonably necessary to participate in that activity. All personal information we do collect can only be accessed by authorized Young Life staff and volunteers, and only those people who require access may see this information for the purposes described above. We work diligently to preserve the confidentiality, security and integrity of that information.

As a ministry to children, Young Life is deeply committed to the safety and welfare of kids. We have policies and procedures designed to ensure compliance with applicable privacy laws and employ generally accepted best practices, especially as it relates to parental notice and consent. Parents have the right to request at any time that the information collected about their child be removed from Young Life’s networks and databases. You can contact Young Life at privacy@younglife.org. 

**California Privacy**

California residents who provide personal information in obtaining products or services for personal, family, or household use are entitled to request and obtain from us once a calendar year information about the customer information we shared, if any, with other businesses for their own direct marketing use. If applicable, this information would include the categories of customer information and the names and addresses of those businesses with which we shared customer information for the immediately prior calendar year.

​

​​​
